Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1900s, 1900-1999; 11 boxes (10 partial)
  - The twelve signs: How a person may know under which sign they are born. Glasgow: 1796, 1967; 36725; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (82 mm. x 139 mm); prospectus for a reprint taken from The Book of Knowledge, including the original preface. Edition limited to 100 copies. Printed in brown and black.
  - Taft, Charles Sabin: Abraham Lincoln's last hours, 1968; 36726; portion of 1 box
    Author: Taft, Charles Sabin
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (112 mm. x 152 mm.); prospectus for three titles from the press, including the Taft's work, Wilfred Hansford Gallienne's "Let Shakespeare Speak," and a yet-untitled miniature book written and illustrated by Dale Nichols. Printed on blue paper.
  - Nichols, Dale: Let there be light, 1968; 36727; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (92 mm. x 140 mm.); prospectus for Nichols' work on Caravaggio. A limited edition, number of copies not given. Text in red and black.
  - Forgue, Norma: [Postcard advertising book sale], 1969; 36707; portion of 1 box
    Author: Forgue, Norma
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (82 mm. x 139 mm.); postcard announcing a book sale, "A list will be sent on request". Addressed to Emerson G. Wulling and postmarked 3 Jul. 1969.
  - Forgue Norman: [Announcement of a book sale], 1969; 36708; portion of 1 box
    Author: Forgue Norman
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (82 mm. x 139 mm.); postcard-sized announcement of a book sale of Forgue's typographic library. Text printed in red.
  - Bembo, Pietro: On Etna, 1969; 36776; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bembo, Pietro
    New York: Bodoni
    Broadside, 8vo; prospectus for the English edition of this work, limited to 125 copies and "bound at the Press with morocco back, the sides covered with Ingres paper, and in a matching slipcase". Place of publication taken from the American distributor, the Chiswick Book Shop, New York, NY.
  - Da Boll, Irene Briggs: Recollections of the Lyceum & Chautauqua circuits...presented in calligraphic format by Raymond F. Da Boll, 1969; 36700; portion of 1 box
    Author: Da Boll, Irene Briggs
    Freeport, Maine: The Bond Wheelwright Company
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for a work on Da Boll, a soprano "on the road"; limited and autographed edition of 250 copies. Text in maroon and black, previous folds.
  - Johnson, Ruth & Foster: Stowaway Sam: The tale of a precocious monkey and his life on the bound wave...illustrated by the authors, 1970; 36644; portion of 1 box
    Author: Johnson, Ruth & Foster
    Meriden, Connecticut: Bayberry Hill Press
    Broadside, folio; illustrated prospectus for "A new book for children of all ages in a very limited edition" offered exclusively at Jepson's Book Store in Meriden, Connecticut. Integral order form at the bottom of Broadside verso. Reproduction of one of the illustrations loosely inserted. Includes the original illustrated envelope in which this prospect came, addressed to Emerson G. Wulling of the Sumac Press, LaCrosse, Wisconsin and postmarked Oct. 23 1970.
  - Morris, Henry: Guilford & Green, 1970; 36689; portion of 1 box
    New York: Bird & Bull Press.
    Broadside, folio; prospectus for a work combining two short manuscripts, Henry Morris's "A Visit to Hayle Hall" and Nathan Guilford's "Dear Friend at Home". "[P]rinted one Bird & Bull and Green's dampened hand made paper." Edition limited to 210 copies. Original address for orders (North Hills, Pennsylvania) has been marked out and replaced with the address label of the Chiswick Book Shop, New York, NY. Previous folds.
  - Terence: Andria: A comedy by Terence. Translated into English by Richard Bernard with 25 illustrations by Albrecht Dürer, 1971; 36771; portion of 1 box
    Author: Terence
    Verona, Italy: Bodoni
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated specimen page (13); edition limited to 100 copies; order form to the American distributor, the Chiswick Book Shop, New York, NY, loosely inserted. A photocopy of an article from the February 4, 1972 TLS is also inserted.
  - Publications available for Christmas gifts, 1972; 39452; portion of 1 box
    12mo, 9 loose leaves in white printed folder as issued; fine. Titles date from 1959 to 1972.
  - Johson, Ruth R.: Sam, M.B.E...illustrated by Foster M. Johnson, 1972; 36645; portion of 1 box
    Author: Johson, Ruth R.
    Broadside, 4to; illustrated prospectus for the fifth book in the series about Sam the precocious monkey, described as "A new amusing book for children" and limited to "just over one hundred numbered copies". Integral order form at the bottom of Broadside verso.
  - Bird & Bull number 13, 1972; 36694; portion of 1 box
    North Hills: Bird & Bull Press
    Single sheet folded twice, oblong 8vo (151 mm. x 235 mm.); prospectus for a work on the press, "printed on Hodgkinson's hand made 'Bird & Bull' dampened before printing. There is a 4 page section printed on paper made from Joe Blumenthal's old pillowcases, and another 4 page section printed on most unusual hand made paper from the Bachaus laboratories. The text is set in 18 point Centaur." Edition limited to 140 copies.
  - A list of Book Club publications available for Chirstmas gifts, 1973; 39450; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 8-sided pamphlet, 12mo; illustrations, printed on blue paper; fine. Titles date from 1959 to 1973. Integral order form.
  - Aesop: The fables of Aesop printed from the Veronese edition of MCCCCLXXIX in Latin verses and the Italian version by Accio Zucco, with the woodcuts newly engraved and coloured after a copy in the British Museum, 1973; 36764; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for this limited edition of 160 copies; photocopy of The Times Literary Supplement, Friday 7 December 1973 review of the piece, titled "A Renaissance book reborn," printed on the inside of bifolium
  - Bauer, Ferdinand: The Australian flower paintings of Ferdinand Bauer., 1974; 36237; portion of 1 box
    London: Basilisk Press
    TLS from Charlene Garry to Waring Jones informing him of the three yearly publications of the Basilisk Press, of which two are "based on previously unpublished material created in the 18th or 19th-centuries and one exact facsimile". The titles included are The Australian flower paintings of Ferdinand Bauer, The red books of Humphry Repton, and a facsimile of The Kelmscott Chaucer. Included are an order form and an addressed envelope to the Basilisk Press. In pristine condition.
  - Morris, Henry: The paper maker: A survey of lesser-known hand paper mills in Europe and North America and an account of a unique publication, with a selective index, 1974; 36698; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for a work originally intended to be an index to the Hercules, Inc. publication of The Paper Maker (1932-1970); "printed on dampened paper made by hand at the Press and specially watermarked...Set in Centaur and Goudy No. 38 types...quarter-bound by Fritz and Trudi Eberhardt in goatskin with paste-paper sides." Edition limited to 175. Text in red and black, previous fold.
  - Voltaire, Francois Arouet de: Epigrams, 1975; 36744; portion of 1 box
    Author: Voltaire, Francois Arouet de
    Broadside, oblong 12mo (122 mm. x 177 mm.); prospectus providing specimen page in its actual size (p. 20); edition limited to no more than 199 copies. Text in purple and black.
  - Starrett, Vincent: Oriental encounters: Two essays in bad taste, 1975; 36742; portion of 1 box
    Author: Starrett, Vincent
    Single folded sheet, 16mo; prospectus provides specimen page (18); edition limited to 249 copies. Text in orange and black.
  - Templeton, Richard H.: The quick brown fox: A chap book...with an introduction by R. Hunter Middleton...Original cover design engraved on wood by Philip Reed, 1975; 36740; portion of 1 box
    Author: Templeton, Richard H.
    Single folded sheet, oblong 16mo; prospectus for the reprint of a work originally published by the Typophiles of New York in 1945. Text in brown and black.
  - Barduzzi, Bernardino: A letter in praise of Verona...in the original Latin text with an English translation by Betty Radice, 1975; 36766; portion of 1 box
    Author: Barduzzi, Bernardino
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for an edition limited to 160 copies; "set in Dante type and printed...on Magnani paper...The binding with a vellum spine has boards covered with a specially decorated Fabriano paper". Integral order form addressed to the American distributor, the Chiswick Book SHop, Sandy Hook, Conn. Printed on yellow paper, previous folds.
  - Broadsides, 1975; 36670; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, 12mo (180 mm.); list of Broadsides and chapbooks from the press printed on grey handmade paper.
  - Dickens, Charles: A Christmas carol in prose. Being a ghost story of Christmas...illustrated by Wolfgang Lederer, 1976; 39541; portion of 1 box
    Author: Dickens, Charles
    Bifolium, large 4to; color illustration, text printed in red and black; fine. Provides 2 specimen pages from this limited edition of 750 copies.
  - Three hundred and sixty-five days, 1976; 36720; portion of 1 box
    120 mm. x 73 mm., unpaginated (two folded sheets, unbound); prospectus also includes other titles from the press.
  - Khayyam, Omar: Lucretius on life & death. Translated in the metre of Omar Khayyam's Rubaiyat by W.H. Mallock. With an introduction by Frank E. Hartman. Decorations in color by Calvin Brazelton, 1976; 36733; portion of 1 box
    Author: Khayyam, Omar
    Bifolium, 16mo; prospectus for this miniature book, with specimen pages (in actual size) 17-18 reprinted here. "The Eden type, designed by R. Hunter Middleton was first hand-set by Norman W. Forgue, then reduced to its present size and printed on Strathmore Pastelle paper...Attractively bound, in full leather by Bela Blau." Edition limited to 249 copies. Text in blue and black.
  - A list of Book Club publications available for Christmas gifts, 1976; 39449; portion of 1 box
    12mo, unpaginated; illustration printed in silver and red; unbound; fine. A list of available titles, published between 1959 and 1976, including those from the Illustrated Keepsake Series. Integral order form printed on back.
  - Feyrer, Gayle: Demon letting: A selection from a novel by Gayle Feyrer with an original serigraph by Cathie Ruggie, 1976; 36669; portion of 1 box
    Author: Feyrer, Gayle
    St. Paul, Minnesota: The Bieler Press
    Broadside, 12mo (171 mm.); text printed in pink and black.
  - Broadsides, 1976; 36671; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, 12mo (182 mm.); postcard listing the Broadsides and chapbooks from the press; addressed to Emerson G. Wulling of La Crosse, WI and postmarked Aug 8 1976.
  - Drake, Albert: Roadsalt: A chapbook of poems, 1976; 36655; portion of 1 box
    Author: Drake, Albert
    Single sheet, folded into eight-sided brochure, 12mo; prospectus for "A limited edition of one hundred and fifty press-numbered copies designed and hand printed by Gerald Lange...Printed with handset Weiss and Broadway types on twelve leaves of imported Frankfurt Creme paper. Our own Bieler handmade was used for the covers and wrappers. An illustration sequence by artist Cathie Ruggie accompanies the poetry." Also makes mention of Gerald Lange's "Starless & Bible Black" and the forthcoming "Demon Legging: a selection from an unpublished novel by Gayle Feyrer".
  - Morris, Henry: Pepper pot, 1977; 36693; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded twice, 8vo; prospectus for this miscellany; "printed on dampened handmade paper...and is quarter bound by E.G. Parrot in Oasis leather with paste paper sides. 250 copies are for sale."
  - Pettis, Charles R.: Cosmic geometry: Tantric transformations. By Charles R. Pettis, III & Rosina Pettis, 1977; 36816; portion of 1 box
    Author: Pettis, Charles R.
    Ithaca, New York: Bliss Press
    Broadside, 8vo (240 mm.); prospectus for the de luxe limited edition of 130 copies, "produced entirely by hand"; stapled to leaf with "Unsolicited comments" and order form; previous folds.
  - McCuen, Harold E.: Entrances and exits. Recollection of Ohio theater, 1978; 36731; portion of 1 box
    Author: McCuen, Harold E.
    16mo, unpaginated (2 folded sheets unbound); text of prospectus by Madeline Forgue; "Strathmore Ivory Smooth Pastelle paper is used as the best medium for reproduction of the many full page photographs. Reproduction of an early stage showing the various advertisements that were popular at the time has been printed in photo brown on a gray-green antique stock and serves as the end-paper. Bound by Bela Blau in lovely soft green Pyroxylin leather over boards." Edition limited to 249 copies.
  - Davis, Frank Marshall: Awakening and other poems, 1978; 36712; portion of 1 box
    Author: Davis, Frank Marshall
    Single folded sheet, 16mo; illustrated prospectus of a collection of poems "buried in the Press files for more than thirty years".
  - Petty, G. Harvey: Alphabet sentences, 1978; 36739; portion of 1 box
    Author: Petty, G. Harvey
    Single folded sheet, 16mo; prospectus for this work on the history and development of the alphabet, "Printed on Strathmore Pastelle antique paper." Edition limited to 249 copies.
  - Defoe, Daniel: Robinson Crusoe, 1979; 36822; portion of 1 box
    Author: Defoe, Daniel
    TLS from Charlene Garry of the Press to H.J. Kittleson (Minneapolis, MN) announcing the publication of the press's edition of Defoe's classic tale; edition limited to 500 copies; includes original envelope in which this prospectus came, postmarked 3 Oct 1979; also includes order form for titles available from the press, a postcard announcing the press' second catalogue, and a pre-addressed envelope.
  - Wolfe, Richard J.: Jacob Bigelow's American medical botany 1817-1821. An examination of the origin, printing, binding and distribution of America's first color plate book. With special emphasis on the manner of making and printing its colored plates, 1979; 36696; portion of 1 box
    Author: Wolfe, Richard J.
    Broadside, long folio (402 mm.); prospectus for a work printed by the press in conjunction with the Boston Medical Library. "Quarter-bound by E.G. Parrot in Oasis leather with floral patterened sides." Edition limited to 300 copies. Previous folds.
  - Barrett, Timothy: Nagashizuki: The Japanese craft of hand papermaking, 1979; 36697; portion of 1 box
    Author: Barrett, Timothy
    Ten-sided brochure printed on two leaves pasted together, 12mo; "composed in 16-point Van Dijck types and printed on hand-made Bird & Bull "Nagashizuki" paper. Quarter-bound by E.G. Parrot in Oasis leather and tips, with decorated Japanese paper sides. 300 copies for sale."
  - Davidson, Gustav: 19th century American juvenile authors: Little-known pseudonyms, 1979; 36714; portion of 1 box
    Author: Davidson, Gustav
    16mo, unpaginated (two folded sheets, unbound); prospectus for Davidson's study, as well as a list of books "on the horizon" from the press. Printed on pale pink sheets.
  - Morley, Christopher: No Crabb--No Christmas, 1979; 36721; portion of 1 box
    Author: Morley, Christopher
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (89 mm. x 140 mm.); postcard prospectus for this Christmas tale. "Edition limited to 249 copies, printed in red, green and lback on Strathmore Pastelle paper. Bound by Bela Blau in Pajco red with morocco grain." Printed in red and black, postcard addressed to Emerson G. Wulling.
  - Zara, Louis: Author's proof, 1979; 36732; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (89 mm. x 140 mm.); postcard prospectus of an edition limited to 249 copies. Addressed to Emerson G. Wulling.
  - Harris, Carla: The man in the smock from the memoirs of an ex-girl Friday, 1979; 36718; portion of 1 box
    Author: Harris, Carla
    Single folded sheet, 16mo; prospectus for a work on Harris' relationship with Norman Forgue. "Decorations by Aimo W. Hill, Jr. printed in two colors." Edition limited to 249 copies.
  - Mardersteig, Giovanni: The officina Bodoni: An account of the work of a hand press 1923-1977. Edited and translated by Hans Schmoller, 1980; 36777; portion of 1 box
    Author: Mardersteig, Giovanni
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus providing the work's table of contents and a specimen page; "Designed by Martino Mardersteig and printed in Verona, Italy at the Stamperia Valdonega, on paper specially made by Cartiera di Sarego, Vicenza." American edition distributed by Oak Knoll Books, New Castle, DE. The work on the Bodoni press is published by Edizioni Valdonega. Previous folds.
  - Franklin, Colin: Fond of printing. Gordon Craig as typographer & illustrator...Foreword by Edward Craig with an essay by Gordon Craig, 1980; 39453; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 12mo; illustration; printed in brown and black; fine. Prospectus for a title published in conjunction with the Typophiles of New York.
  - Three new titles, 1980; 36674; portion of 1 box
    Madison, WI: The Bieler Press
    Bifolium, long 4to (253 mm.); prospectus for the following works from the press: "Common ground," a collaboration between poet Gerald Williams and artist Ben-Zion Shechter; "Billy the Kid," a prose poem by Shuntaro Tanikawa; and "First Z Poems," by Dannis Saleh.
  - Buckley, Christopher: Pentimento, 1980; 36672; portion of 1 box
    Author: Buckley, Christopher
    Broadside, long 4to (265 mm.); prospectus for a chapbook of Buckley's poems, illustrated by Gerald Lange. Also includes a short list of other titles available from the press. Previous fold.
  - Gilgun, John: Everything that has been shall be again: The reincarnation fables of John Gilgun, 1981; 36673; portion of 1 box
    Author: Gilgun, John
    Broadside, long 4to (300 mm.); illustrated prospectus for a chapbook of Gilgun's bestiary, illustrated with a wood engraving by Michael McCurdy of the Penmaen Press. "Hand set in Bembo and Poliphilus type are used for the text and display. The engravings are printed in dark brown, the type in black, on Tovil paper from Barcham Green. The book is hand bound in cloth by Scott Husby. Brown Roma paper from the Fabriano mill is used for the endsheets and slipcase." Edition limited to 150 numbered copies signed by the author and the artist and initaled by the printer. Previous fold.
  - Bliss, Carey S.: A pair on printing: Atkyns' The original and growth of printing. William Caslon and the first English type specimen book. Reproduced in facsimile..., 1982; 36690; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bliss, Carey S.
    New Castle, DE: Bird & Bull Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for this facsimile; place of publication from the distributor, Oak Knoll Books. "Introductory texts composed in Van Dijck types and printed on Frankfurt paper. The facsimiles are printed on Mohawk Text, and the book was bound by Gray Parrot in Dutch natural linen with printed spine label." Edition limited to 500 copies.
  - Alvarado, Juan Bautista: Vignettes of early California: childhood reminiscences...A heretofore unpublished account of Spanish & Mexican California, 1982; 39473; portion of 1 box
    Author: Alvarado, Juan Bautista
    Bifolium, 8vo; decorative border printed in black and grey; fine. Prospectus of the first publication of this 19th-century manuscript, designed and printed by Patrick Reagh in an edition limited to 650 copies and bound by Kater-Crafts Bookbinders. Order form laid in.
  - Cadnum, Michael: The morning of the massacre, 1982; 36657; portion of 1 box
    Author: Cadnum, Michael
    Saint Paul, MN: The Bieler Press
    Broadside, 8vo (198 mm.); illustrated Broadside for the author's first published collection of poetry. Title page illustration by Kathy Shallock. "The chapbook was printed with hand-set Bembo type accompanied by fine fule in a second color. The physical book consists of a double signature of white Arches Text Wove mouldmade paper hand bound into soft covers by Richard de Bas Chamois Chine Blanc handmade paper...Available in an author signed edition of 150 numbered copies."
  - Butterworth, Elizabeth: Amazon parrots, 1983; 37802; portion of 1 box
    Author: Butterworth, Elizabeth
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 4to; prospectus for this pictorial monograph on parrot with 28 plates of paintings by Butterworth; text by Rosemary Low. Limited to 500 copies, printed by CTD Printers and handbound by Smith and Settle. Specimen plate laid in.
  - Guthrie, James: The miniature world of Norman Forgue...with an introduction by Ward K. Schori, 1983; 36724; portion of 1 box
    Author: Guthrie, James
    16mo, unpaginated (3 folded sheets unbound); prospectus for a limited edition of 249 copies. Handwritten note, "Hope all is well in your world, Norman," loosely inserted.
  - Snyder, Dee: The ABCs of Baker Street: Guide to the Holmsian habitat...introduction by John Bennett, Shaw, 1983; 36723; portion of 1 box
    Author: Snyder, Dee
    16mo, unpaginated (two folded sheets, unbound); prospectus for this study of Sherlock Holmesiana, limited to 249 copies and "Bound in Pyroxlin leather".
  - [Maitland, Terrence]: The contagion of war., 1983; 36256; portion of 1 box
    Author: [Maitland, Terrence]
    Boston: Boston Publishing Company
    Bifolium, 4to, prospectus of the companion piece to American takes over. With black and white photographic illustrations of scenes from the Vietnam War. Includes quotes from American veterans.
  - Franklin, Colin: Doves Press: The start of a worry. Edited with an introduction by Colin Franklin. Foreward by Michael Hornby, 1983; 36908; portion of 1 box
    Austin, Texas: Bridwell Library, Southern Methodist University
    Broadside, 4to (298 mm.); prospectus for this history of the Doves Press, limited to 275 copies and printed at the Bird & Bull Press "in Centaur types on Bugra Bütten paper, bound in cloth-backed Fabriano paper over boards". Text in maroon and black, previous fold.
  - Buckley, Christopher: Five small meditations on summer & birds, 1984; 36678; portion of 1 box
    St. Paul, MN: The Bieler Press
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (112 mm. x 152 mm.); postcard prospectus for a chapbook of Buckley's poems, "handset in Lutetia & Egmont Decorated Initials (watercolored) and printed on Lana Laid, a French mouldmade paper. The sheets were sewn into soft covers of Richard de Bas Papier A Inclusions Florales (a white handmade sheet formed with real flowers!). The edition consists of 200 numbered copies." Postcard addressed to Emerson G. Wulling of the Sumac Press, LaCrosse, WI and postmarked September, 1984.
  - Catalogue 4, 1985; 36815; portion of 1 box
    London: Basilisk Press & Bookshop
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (105 mm. x 148 mm.); illustrated postcard prospectus for the press' fourth catalogue, advertised as listing more than 600 in-print titles. Addressed to Emerson G. Wulling of the Sumac Press and postmarked May 3 1985.
  - Hart, Joanne: The village schoolmaster, 1985; 36656; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hart, Joanne
    Minneapolis, Minnesota: The Bieler Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for a work "designed by Emily Mason and Gerald Lange. Carol Ann Smith, a Saint Paul artist, provided the title page illustration. The chapbook was hand printed with Poliphilus and Blado types on Ragston paper. The end-sheets are on Japanese origin and the covers are an English handmade from the mill of Barcham Green. The edition is limited to 200 numbered and author signed copies."
  - Van Winckel, Nance: The 24 doors, 1985; 36675; portion of 1 box
    Author: Van Winckel, Nance